Git and GitHub Study Notes
===========================

Here's a comprehensive guide for each topic:

---

**1. Git basics (init, add, commit, status)**
   The foundational commands for starting and tracking a project locally:
   - `git init`: Creates a new repository in the current directory
   - `git add`: Stages changes for commit (can use . to add all)
   - `git commit`: Saves a snapshot of your staged changes with a message
   - `git status`: Shows which files are modified, staged, or untracked
   
   Example workflow:
   $ git init my-project
   $ cd my-project
   $ git add README.md
   $ git commit -m "Add initial README"

**2. Branching and merging**
   Branches let you work on features or fixes in isolation without affecting the main codebase:
   - `git branch`: List, create, or delete branches
   - `git checkout -b [branch-name]`: Create and switch to a new branch
   - `git merge [branch-name]`: Merge changes from specified branch into current branch
   - Merging brings those changes back together when ready
   
   Common pattern: feature branching workflow

**3. GitHub workflow (push, pull, clone)**
   How your local Git work connects to the cloud:
   - `git clone [url]`: Copies a remote repo to your local machine
   - `git push origin [branch]`: Uploads your commits to the remote repository
   - `git pull origin [branch]`: Fetches and merges latest changes from remote
   
   This enables synchronization between local and cloud repositories.

**4. Collaboration and pull requests**
   The process of contributing to a shared codebase:
   - Fork a repository to create your own copy
   - Create a feature branch for your changes
   - Push your branch and open a pull request (PR)
   - Teammates review your code with suggestions
   - Once approved, merge the PR into the main branch
   
   Pull requests enable code review and quality assurance before merging.

---

BEGINNER CHECKLIST
==================

□ Git Setup
  □ Install Git on your computer
  □ Configure git user name with: git config --global user.name "Your Name"
  □ Configure git email with: git config --global user.email "your@email.com"
  □ Verify settings with: git config --list

□ First Repository
  □ Create a new directory for your project
  □ Navigate into the directory (cd your-project)
  □ Initialize git with: git init
  □ Create or add files to the project
  □ Stage files with: git add .
  □ Create first commit with: git commit -m "Initial commit"

□ Understanding Git Workflow
  □ Make a change to a file
  □ Check status with: git status
  □ Stage changes with: git add [filename]
  □ Commit with: git commit -m "descriptive message"
  □ Repeat this cycle several times to get comfortable

□ Working with Branches
  □ Create a new branch with: git branch feature/my-feature
  □ Switch to it with: git checkout feature/my-feature
  □ Make changes and commit them
  □ Switch back to main: git checkout main
  □ Merge your feature: git merge feature/my-feature
  □ Delete branch: git branch -d feature/my-feature

□ Remote Repository (GitHub)
  □ Create a new repository on GitHub
  □ Copy the repository URL
  □ Link local repo: git remote add origin [URL]
  □ Push to GitHub: git push -u origin main
  □ Pull latest changes: git pull origin main

□ Collaboration
  □ Fork a repository from GitHub
  □ Clone your fork to local machine
  □ Create a feature branch
  □ Make improvements and commit
  □ Push branch to your fork
  □ Create a pull request on GitHub
  □ Wait for review and corrections if needed
  □ Merge when approved

□ Practice Scenarios
  □ Complete: Create, edit, commit, and push a simple project
  □ Complete: Create a feature branch and merge it back
  □ Complete: Clone a repository and make a pull request
  □ Complete: Resolve a simple merge conflict (if encountered)

KEY TAKEAWAYS
=============
✓ Git tracks changes in your code over time
✓ Commits are snapshots of your project at specific points
✓ Branches allow parallel development without interference
✓ Remote repositories (GitHub) enable collaboration
✓ Pull requests facilitate code review and quality control
✓ Practice is key to becoming proficient with Git
